Today's date is November 3rd, is the 21st of חשון Cheshvan and
we're starting on ז' עמוד ב'. Zayin Amud Bet. My name is
Dan Maryus, I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer because he is at
a ברית, Bris, so we wish מזל טוב Mazel Tov to the
family.
מזל טוב! Mazel Tov!
And we continue with ז' עמוד ב' Zayin Amud Bet towards the
top, the גמרא Gemara starts ומאיימין עליה. Uma'amin Aleha. So the משנה
Mishnah had said that the בית דין Beis Din tries to impress
upon the woman who is going to go through the סוטה Sotah
ritual the severity of what she's doing because of the concern, the
משנה Mishnah said that, let me just find the exact line, that
they should not erase God's name because it's written בקדושה. BiKdusha.
Sorry, it's right towards the beginning of the
משנה. Mishnah. מאיימין עליה על ידי נפשות, Ma'amin Aleha Al Yedei Nefashos,
they impress upon her the severity of what's going to happen just
like we do with witnesses who are testifying to a capital crime,
because why?
אסור לשמו הגדול שנכתב בקדושה שלא ימחה על המים, Asur Lishmo HaGadol
SheNichtav BiKdusha Shelo Yimacheh Al HaMayim, so that we shouldn't erase God's
name for no reason, because part of the severity of this סוטה
Sotah ritual is that God's name is written in the מגילת סוטה
Megillas Sotah and then the words, the ink of the מגילה Megillah
are erased into the water, scraped off into the water, and so
I mean part of that is the beauty of the סוטה Sotah
ritual that we see from the אגדתא, Aggadata, God is willing to
have God's name erased in order to bring שלום בית Shalom Bayis
to this couple. However, it is, there is an איסור Issur to
erase God's name, so we want to prevent the erasure of God's
name if at all possible. So ומאיימין עליה. Uma'amin Aleha. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask a question, ורמינהו כדרך שמאיימין עליה
שלא תשתה כך מאיימין עליה שתשתה. Ureminhu Kederech Shema'amin Aleha Shelo Tishteh
Kach Ma'amin Aleha Shetishteh. So I don't understand, we have a ברייתא
Braisa from the תוספתא Tosefta that actually expands on this notion and
says, just like we scare her into not drinking, so too we
scare her into drinking. So what does that even mean? How can
you have it both ways? If we're saying that the whole point
of scaring her is that she shouldn't end up going through the
ritual because we don't want to erase God's name, then what does
it mean to scare her into drinking? Okay. אומרים לה בתי אם
ברור לך הדבר שטהורה את עמדי על בורייך ושתי, Omrim Lah Bitti
Im Barur Lach HaDavar SheTehorah At Omdi Al Boryich U'shti, if it's
so clear to you that you have not committed adultery, עמדי על
בורייך, Omdi Al Boryich, you're going to remain
healthy and you should drink the water, לפי שאין מים המאררים דומים
אלא לסם יבש שמונח על בשר חי,
Lefi She'ein Mayim HaMe'arerim Domim Ela
LeSam Yavesh Shemunach Al Basar Chai, because the water, the bitter water
is like a dry medicine which is put onto raw flesh, onto
exposed wound, אם יש שם מכה מחלחל ויורד, Im Yesh Sham Maka
Mechalchel VeYored,
if there is a wound there, then the סם, Sam, the medicine
will dissolve in the moisture of the blood and penetrate into the
skin.
Okay. אם יש שם מכה מחלחל ויורד אין שם מכה אינו מועיל
כלום,
Im Yesh Sham Maka Mechalchel VeYored Ein
Sham Maka Eino Mo'il Kelum, but if there is no wound, then
it won't do anything. In other words to say, if she's innocent
and she drinks the water then it's not going to do anything
and therefore you've made God's name erase for no reason, but if
she did something wrong, if sorry the opposite, if she's innocent of
the adultery then the whole point of the ritual is to prove
her innocence and therefore it's beneficial for her at this point to
actually go through the ritual. So there are two different stages. So
we're trying to say, okay, לא קשיא כאן קודם שנמחקה המגילה כאן
לאחר שנמחקה המגילה. Lo Kashya Kan Kodem Shenimchakah HaMegillah Kan Le'achar Shenimchakah
HaMegillah.
So before they have erased the מגילת סוטה, Megillas Sotah, then we
try to encourage the woman to admit to having done adultery so
that she should not have to go through the ritual and erase
God's name only for her then to have this miraculous punishment come
about. On the flip side, if they have already erased God's name,
then you don't want it to have been for no reason, so
you want to encourage her to drink and to try to tell
her really you should think that you're innocent, really you should go
through with it because it's going to be beneficial for you.
ואומר לפניה, Ve'omer Lefaneha,
so what do you say before her?
So the משנה Mishnah had said they say before her דברים שאינם
כדי לשמען, Devarim She'einam Kedai Lishmo'an, there are things that are not
suitable to be heard and they tell them to her anyway. So
what does that mean? Okay, so תנו רבנן אומר לפניה דברים של
אגדה ומעשים שאירעו בכתובים הראשונים. Tanu Rabbanan Omer Lefaneha Devarim Shel Aggada
U'Ma'asim She'iru BaKesuvim HaRishonim.
We tell her אגדה, Aggada,
אגדתות, Aggadatos, some kind of a story that's going to inspire her
or arouse her emotions about this activity.
Why is it not כדי לשמען? Kedai Lishmo'an?
So we're going to hear why.
One second, is it כדי Kedai or אינם כדי לשמען? Einam Kedai
Lishmo'an? It says מעשים שאירעו בכתובים, Ma'asim She'iru BaKesuvim, דברים של
אגדה ומעשים שאירעו בכתובים הראשונים כגון אשר חכמים יגידו ולא כחדו מאבותם,
Devarim Shel Aggada U'Ma'asim She'iru BaKesuvim HaRishonim Kagon Asher Chachamim Yaggidu
VeLo Kichadu Me'avosam,
it's a פסוק Pasuk from איוב Iyov saying about how חכמים Chachamim
will speak about this, ולא כחדו מאבותם, VeLo Kichadu Me'avosam, that you
shouldn't have this fear from earlier generations because what's the problem? מעשים
שאירעו בכתובים הראשונים, Ma'asim She'iru BaKesuvim HaRishonim, so if you look in
what רש"י Rashi says, דברים הכתובים בתורה שנעשו בימים הראשונים, Devarim HaKesuvim
BaTorah SheNa'asu BeYamim HaRishonim, things that happened in earlier days, כגון אגדה
זו דאשר חכמים יגידו ויודו על חטאתם, Kagon Aggada Zo De'asher Chachamim
Yaggidu VeYodu Al Chattatam,
because earlier wise people in previous times were able to admit to
their sin and repent for it.
And why are they אינם כדי לשמען?
Einam Kedai Lishmo'an? We're going to hear why in just a second.
Two examples, so what are the two examples? Okay, יהודה הודה ולא
בוש. Yehuda Hodeh VeLo Bosh. יהודה Yehuda admitted his sin and was
not embarrassed. מה היה סופו? mah haya sofo? נחל חיי עולם הבא.
nachal chayei olam haba. So יהודה Yehuda was able to then inherit
עולם הבא. olam haba. ראובן הודה ולא בוש, Reuven hoda velo bosh,
and ראובן Reuven admitted his sin and he was not embarrassed. מה
היה סופו? mah haya sofo? נחל חיי עולם הבא. nachal chayei olam
haba. And ראובן Reuven was also able to get עולם הבא. olam
haba. Here the rabbis are going against their general principle, which we've
seen in מגילה, Megilla, which is that generally we think, at least
from the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh perspective, יהודה Yehuda and
ראובן Reuven did not actually do anything wrong. Okay, so there's some
מחלוקת machlokes about it, but we say that we don't, when we
read those פרשיות parshiyot in the תורה, Torah, we don't have the
תרגום targum so that people shouldn't be misled by the פשט peshat
understanding of the story of ראובן. Reuven. The story of ראובן Reuven
sounds like from the פשט peshat that ראובן Reuven literally slept with
his stepmother,
and חז"ל Chazal tell us that it was something less severe.
According to one of the times he did, fine, but at least
according to the way this גמרא Gemara is saying, it's דברים שלא
כדאי לשמען, devarim shelo kedai lishoman, these are things which you really
shouldn't be hearing because it's either embarrassing for someone who really was
a big צדיק tzadik or it's embarrassing for someone who's mentioned in
the תורה. Torah. This goes into the major question in Israel now,
or perhaps from a few years ago, the debate about learning תנ"ך
בגובה העיניים, Tanach begova ha-einayim, how much can we relate to characters
in תנ"ך Tanach as real personalities, as real characters, and how much
do we have to consider them as people who are so far
beyond our level that we can't even question and things like that.
So יהודה, Yehuda, יהודה's Yehuda relationship with תמר, Tamar, his daughter-in-law, and
how much was that really the right thing for him to have
been doing at that time, how much was it not the right
thing for him to have been doing at that time? And then
again in the פשט peshat it sounds like he says, "I made
a mistake," he says, צדקה ממני, tzadka mimeni, "She was correct and
I was wrong." So at least the way this is being read,
we take a value from the פשט peshat of these stories even
if in other places חז"ל Chazal are telling us we have to
read those stories with another layer of meaning. So that's exactly the
point of this, which is that they're authorizing even reading a story
the wrong way
in order to...
Reading it how it sounds. Well, that's the question about how much
is the value of פשט peshat in
study of תנ"ך, Tanach, especially from the rabbinic perspective. The רמ"א Rama
quotes this, I think it's in one of his תשובות teshuvot in—now
I'm forgetting which סימן siman it was, it's one of the תשובות
teshuvot of the רמ"א—he Rama says this is a proof that basically
embarrassing a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is part of what's allowed in
terms of more broadly the process of סוטה, Sotah, getting people to
confess their sins, getting people to bring שלום בית shalom bayit and
to repair their relationships. So this is an example of that. Okay,
so we see here,
okay, we're not taking the story of דוד David because that's separate.
Okay, so the story of דוד David is an interesting question as
well. The rabbis also tell us that דוד David didn't sin and
he's not mentioned here. It's an interesting question, but דוד David is
a descendant of יהודה Yehuda and in a certain sense has the
same parallel to that story. Yes?
The דוד ובת שבע David u-Bat Sheva narrative doesn't even appear in
דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim.
That's a good point. Okay, fine. Okay, ראובן הודה ולא בוש Reuven
hoda velo bosh מה היה סופו mah haya sofo נחל חיי עולם
הבא. nachal chayei olam haba. So they both get עולם הבא. olam
haba. ומה שכרן? u-mah scharan? The גמרא Gemara asks, so what was
the reward? What do you mean ומה שכרן? u-mah scharan? בדיקאמרינא, bi-de'ka'amrina,
we just said they both got עולם הבא. olam haba. אלא מה
שכרן בעולם הזה? ela mah scharan ba-olam ha-zeh? What's their reward even
in this world? So the פסוק pasuk says להם לבדם ניתנה הארץ,
lahem levadam nitna ha'aretz,
which is seemingly a kind of a hint to the fact that
ראובן Reuven was among the tribes that first got their inheritance on
the east side of the ירדן. Yarden. So ראובן Reuven was able
to really have the first חלק chelek in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
ולא עבר זר בתוכם. velo avar zar betocham. בשלמא ביהודה אשכחן דהודי
דכתיב, bishlama bi-Yehuda ashkechan de-hodi di-chtiv,
so we know that יהודה Yehuda admitted his sin because it says
ויכר יהודה ויאמר צדקה ממני, vayaker Yehuda vayomer tzadka mimeni, because it
says explicitly in the פסוק pasuk that יהודה Yehuda admitted to having
done something wrong. אלא ראובן מנלן דהודי? ela Reuven mena-lan de-hodi? So
how do we know that ראובן Reuven admitted to having done something
wrong? דאמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן מה דכתיב de-amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yochanan mah dichtetiv יחי ראובן ואל
ימות? yechi Reuven ve'al yamot? So what does it mean when משה
Moshe is giving his ברכות brachot to the tribes at the end
of ספר דברים sefer Devarim and משה Moshe says יחי ראובן ואל
ימות, yechi Reuven ve'al yamot, ראובן Reuven should live and not die,
and then it says וזאת ליהודה. ve-zot l'Yehuda. רש"י Rashi notes that
the only one of the ברכות brachot that starts with seemingly unusual
word וזאת ve-zot is the ברכה bracha for יהודה. Yehuda. So it
seems to be a connection between what ראובן Reuven did and what
יהודה Yehuda did. It starts ראובן Reuven and then יהודה, Yehuda, and
then again some of the מפרשים mefarshim they are discussing the question
why are they out of order, why are שמעון Shimon and לוי
Levi left out, things like that. So here it's making a connection
between ראובן Reuven living and not dying, and then what did יהודה
Yehuda do? יהודה Yehuda had admitted his sin. כל אותן שנים שהיו
ישראל במדבר היו עצמותיו של יהודה מתגלגלים בארון. kol otan shanim she'hayu
Yisrael bamidbar hayu atzmotav shel Yehuda mitgalglim ba'aron.
So the entire time that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael were in the
מדבר midbar for 40 years, the bones of יהודה Yehuda were rolling
around in the coffin עד שעמד משה וביקש עליו רחמים ad she'amad
Moshe u'vikesh alav rachamim and משה Moshe prayed for him. אמר לפניו
ריבונו של עולם, amar lefanav ribbono shel olam, מי גרם לראובן שהודה,
mi garam l'Reuven she'hoda, who was it who was responsible for the
fact that ראובן Reuven did תשובה? teshuvah? It was יהודה. Yehuda. So
the fact that יהודה Yehuda was suffering for his sin, but was
in the end rewarded by having that punishment cease after 40 years
because of דווקא davka the fact that it was his personality and
his character and his having admitted his sin. inspired ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
to do תשובה *teshuvah*. It's an interesting thing: it's not because of
the fact that he did תשובה *teshuvah* himself, but because he inspired
ראובן *Reuven* to do תשובה *teshuvah* that he gets rewarded with this:
וזאת ליהודה *Vezot liYehuda* מיד *miyad* שמע ה' קול יהודה *Shema Adonai
kol Yehuda*. And that's why the next line right after that is
that God God heard, as if, יהודה'ס *Yehuda's* cries out and and
therefore that he was rewarded in that way. אבריה דשפי *Evarai deshaffa*
because what is it what was it that he was praying about?
That his limbs were were disjointed out of their sockets. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* notes a connection to the one of the טרפות *trefot* in
חולין *Chullin* on דף נ"ב עמוד ב' *daf nun-bet amud-bet* is בוקא
דאטמא דשף בדוכתיה *buka de'atma deshaf biduchteh*, the hip socket is dislocated
out of the hip joint, that is one of the טרפות *trefot*,
and שף *shaf* means that the joint was out of place. So
אבריה דשפי *evarai deshaffa* that his limbs were were dislocated or somehow
that even in death this was a punishment for יהודה *Yehuda*.
So יהודה *Yehuda* should have been we all suspect having even though
he said don't bring it back to you I'll be sending to
you forever, he did, but it all worked out well. So יהודה
*Yehuda* still being are we trying to say I mean there's a
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* in גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that the reason why you're
still because of his quote-unquote sin of תמר *Tamar*? Like in other
words, why was there?
Somehow because of the sin of תמר *Tamar* in some way it
seems like יהודה *Yehuda* was punished for forty years that his while
they were once they had exhumed his his bones from מצרים *Mitzrayim*
and they were bringing them to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* along with
the other שבטים *shevatim* of the other of יעקב'ס *Yaakov's* twelve sons,
that he was being punished in some kind of a posthumous way.
His bones couldn't relax and therefore after this time at the end
of
forty years because רש"י Rashi *Rashi* makes the whole thing about נידוי
על תנאי *niduy al tenai*. Oh we're going to get yeah רש"י
*Rashi* mentioned. But it doesn't make so much sense, I mean at
least you know well let's keep going.
Okay, so what was another punishment that יהודה *Yehuda* had? ולא הוה
קא עיילי ליה למתיבתא דרקיעא *Velo hava ka'aylin lei lemtivta dirakia*, they
wouldn't accept him in in the ישיבה *yeshiva* in שמים *shamayim* up
in heaven, they wouldn't listen to him in, you know of course
I love whenever the rabbis imagine that heaven is like a בית
מדרש *beit midrash*. They wouldn't let him in, they wouldn't accept, so
we see, okay,
ואל עמו תביאנו *Ve'el amo tevi'enu*, so then
they would bring him in, okay? ולא הוה קא ידע למישקל *Velo
hava ka yada mishkal*, probably should be like you see on the
side from the מסורת הש"ס *Masoret HaShas*, למיטרח *lemitra* like שקלא וטריה
*shakla vetarya* בשמעתא *bishmayta* בהדי רבנן Rabbanan *bahadei rabanan*, that they had
שקלא וטריה *shakla vetarya*, they had the back and forth of the
debate in in the בית מדרש *beit midrash* בהדי רבנן *bahadei rabanan*.
So he couldn't do it, they wouldn't let him participate in the
debates in שמים *shamayim* even once they let him in. So then
ידיו רב לו *yadav rav lo*, his hands are are strong for
him, his hands are are good for him, okay? So that was
then reparations for that. ולא הוה קא סליק ליה שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא
*Velo hava kasalik lei shemayta aliba dehilkhata*, he was unable to teach
or to learn the סוגיות sugyot *sugyot* finally until their halakhic conclusion.
ועזר מצריו תהיה *Ve'ezer mitsarav tihyeh* and therefore משה *Moshe* blessed him
ועזר מצריו תהיה *ve'ezer mitsarav tihyeh* that the תורה *Torah* should be
a protection for him from his enemies, that that he should be
able to learn the סוגיות *sugyot* אליבא דהלכתא *aliba dehilkhata*. It's interesting
to note the rabbis often put an emphasis on studying תלמוד *Talmud*
אליבא דהלכתא *aliba dehilkhata*, that the conclusion we should be learning halakhic
conclusions from our סוגיות *sugyot* so of course that's why we spend
all of our time here in סוטה Sotah
*Sotah* learning אגדתא Aggadata, *Aggadata*.
Well obviously we are superior to those rabbis because we don't do
that today.
Well we have some of each, we have to make sure you
know we pay attention when there are halakhic conclusions in the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* we pay attention. So we'll keep going. Okay, בשלמא יהודה
דאודי *Bishlama Yehuda de'odi*,
so we say fine it's okay to understand that יהודה *Yehuda* had
admitted his sin, כי היכי דלא תישרף תמר *kehikhi delo tishraf Tamar*
because the whole whole reason that יהודה *Yehuda* had to admit his
sin in public was so that תמר *Tamar* shouldn't have been
published punished and killed, burned, burned at the stake it seems. It's
interesting to note as well חז"ל *Chazal* when they understand the the
punishment of שריפה sreifah *sereifa* which there I think four, four עבירות
*aveirot* in the תורה *Torah* that you get punished with שריפה *sereifa*,
I could be wrong about the four, I have to check.
So שריפה *sereifa* in חז"ל *Chazal* doesn't mean burning at the stake,
it means an internal burning and that's a very fascinating סוגיא sugya.
*sugya* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* we're going to see it's going to come
up in just a second we'll talk about it in just a
second. So תישרף תמר *tishraf Tamar*. אלא ראובן *Ela Reuven*, למה ליה
לאודי *lama lei le'odi*? So why should ראובן *Reuven* have admitted his
sin at all? There's no תועלת *to'elet*, there was no reason for
him to do that. You mean in in the end?
He admits it to יעקב
*Yaakov*.
Okay, so it's interesting, so what's the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* answer going to
be? ואמר רב ששת *Ve'amar Rav Sheshet* what do רב ששת *Rav
Sheshet* say? חציפא עלי דמיפרט חטאיה *Chatsifa alai demafrat chatatei*, he was
worried about publicizing his sin, כי היכי דלא תחשדו אחוהי *kehikhi delo
tishdu achohi*, he was worried that that his brothers would be suspected
for what he had done and therefore he had to make a
public declaration. It's one thing.
So he made a public declaration?
So that's what they're saying, they're saying he had to make a
public apology.
Oh sorry he made public apology to
The assumption is that normally whatever it was that he did wrong,
he would have gone to apologize to יעקב personally or something, but
other people who would have heard about what happened, but they didn't
know who was responsible, they would have suspected any of his other
brothers. He had to make a public apology to know that it
was him and not anyone else, that no one else should be
חשוד chashud for that sin. It's interesting to see you know there
with the רמב"ם Rambam in particular where it's really from the גמרא
Gemara notes that for different types of sins it's better to do
a private apology just between a person and God or a public
apology. מצוות בין אדם לחברו Mitzvot bein adam l'chaveiro you have to
publicize the fact that you sinned and you're doing you're publicly apologizing
for it because you really hurt another person and that's part of
the way you make it better. But for מצוות בין אדם למקום
Mitzvot bein adam l'Makom it's better to just keep it between you
and God. There's no reason to publicize the fact that you did
that sin. That's just adding something else on to you know why
should you make that public? Okay, says the גמרא, Gemara אם אמרת
טמאה אני. im amart tameia ani. So what if the woman admits
that she had had adultery? שמע מינה, shma mina, so what do
we do? We say we break her כתובה, ketubah, שוברים כתובתה. shovrim
ketubatah. What do we mean שוברים? shovrim?
We break the כתובה? ketubah? שמע מינה כותבים שובר. shma mina kotvim
shovar. We write a receipt for the כתובה. ketubah.
It's interesting to note if you look in the last רש"י on
the page
that the alternative
sorry not up to that yet one second. Okay, so שמע מינה
כותבים שובר. shma mina kotvim shovar. We write a receipt. אמר אביי
תני מקרע. amar Abaye tani mikra.
So shouldn't we say no, no, no, you tear up the כתובה?
ketubah? We should change the way the משנה Mishna reads. It means
שוברים, shovrim, you break it, you just tear up the כתובה. ketubah.
If you tear up a שטר, shtar, if you tear up the
deed, then there's no way to claim the debt. So the question
is what's the better way to ensure that the כתובה ketubah has
been paid in a case where you would pay the כתובה ketubah
or a case where it hasn't been paid that it should not
get paid in the future? One way is to write a receipt
that cancels out the שטר shtar but you leave the initial שטר
shtar hanging and one is to just tear up the initial שטר.
shtar. אמר ליה רבא amar lei Rava or כתובה. ketubah. Okay, but
what's the point of having to keep in other words on who
is the onus to make sure that things are registered properly? Is
it the person who's trying to claim the debt and then they
have to then have a receipt that says accounts are all settled
or is it on the responsibility of the person who is closing
the debt?
Exactly, she doesn't get the כתובה. ketubah.
So give the husband the receipt that he does not have to
pay the כתובה. ketubah. So אמר ליה רבא והא שוברת קתני. amar
lei Rava v'ha shoveret katani. Does it say you break it? So
you can't change the משנה. Mishna. What are you saying אביי? Abaye?
אלא אמר רבא במקום שאין כותבים כתובה עסקינן. ela amar Rava bimkom
she'ein kotvim ketubah askinan. No, we're talking about a case where they
don't write a physical document for the כתובה. ketubah. The כתובה ketubah
is done entirely orally. It's an interesting note if you read all
the different סוגיות across ש"ס, Shas, it sounds like in some places
כתובה ketubah is דאורייתא, d'Oraita, in some places כתובה ketubah is דרבנן.
d'Rabbanan. And which aspect of it are which? And the רמב"ם Rambam
has a very interesting formulation in the beginning of הלכות אישות. Hilchot
Ishut. The רמב"ם Rambam says that the מצווה mitzvah of קידושין kiddushin
is that you should get married
בקידושין ובכתובה. bekiddushin uv'ketubah. The כתובה ketubah is part of the מצווה
mitzvah of קידושין. kiddushin. Interesting things to note there in the רמב"ם
Rambam
and to note what do you mean a case a place where
they don't write a physical document for the כתובה? ketubah? Then how
would that even work? So רש"י here at the bottom says two
possibilities. Either number one,
משינתגרשה, mishenitgarsha, when she gets divorced, מוציאה גיטה וגובה בה. motzi'ah gittah
v'govah bah. She then brings the גט get itself as a proof
that she is divorced and she can claim the כתובה. ketubah. או
כשנתאלמנה, o k'shenitalmena, if she is widowed, מביאה עדי מיתה וגובה. mevi'ah
edei mitah v'govah. It's a much more involved process. She would actually
have to bring witnesses who saw the fact that her husband is
dead in order to be able to claim from his estate.
Okay, so that was for strict then actually being able to remarry.
Exactly, because she would only need one. One, right.
But interesting to note as well well by ממונות, mamonot, המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, you need a very strong claim
in order to extract money. Also to note here it's a much
more involved and difficult process than just having the כתובה. ketubah. In
a certain sense you could see this as part of the historical
development of the כתובה ketubah as a document that at first it
was an oral agreement and then the רבנים rabbanim realized that it
was a huge pain for the woman to try to do this
in a case of if she were widowed or divorced and so
then they instituted that she could just have a שטר shtar in
her hand and bring that.
Okay. All strange that I mean shouldn't the why are we relying
on the woman to if we're talking about שובר, shovar, why are
we relying on the woman? Like why doesn't the בית דין Beit
Din just issue a receipt saying well that's what it is.
The בית דין Beit Din writes the שובר shovar and gives it
to the husband that it
was paid. Okay,
שוברת כתובתה shoveret ketubatah whatever, she breaks it is not what again?
So the way they're trying to read it into the משנה Mishna
is interesting because really the משנה's Mishna לשון lashon says שוברת, shoveret,
she breaks her כתובה. ketubah. It sounds really like what אביי Abaye
is saying, קורעת, kora'at, ממקרע, mimikra, she just tears up the שטר.
shtar. It shouldn't be anything more than that.
This is what we considered on this before because I can see
part of the issue. So why is it that they say something
bad about you?
So you ask a very good question and later פוסקים poskim have
dealt with how to actually put it into play in cases where
things like that are sensitive issues, meaning you're actually navigating not just
your relationship with this other person but much more broadly. But if
you say someone like someone embezzled money from many different people, they
really have to make a public apology.
They can't just
apologize to each person involved. I think there's a moving יציאה yetziah
though. And for sure... עיין שם. Ayin sham.
There's a lot more to be said about it. We have to
keep going. But yeah, no, it's a great question. Meaning, how do
you put it into practice is really a much more difficult question
than the way it sounds like on paper.
Meaning, if I make someone miserable, of course I have to apologize
in public so everyone else knows. Yeah. True. It seems to me
it could be magnifying. Yup.
Well, that's exactly their concern. Their concern is that by ראובן publicly
apologizing, he's actually making more of a problem. They said no, he
was concerned that his brothers would be חשוד chashud and therefore he
had to override and suppress that concern. Okay, דאימר אמרת טהורה אני,
De'imar amart tehorah ani, we're in the last line of ז עמוד
ב. Zayin amud bais. דאימר אמרת טהורה אני,
מעלין אותה לשערי מזרח.
De'imar amart tehorah
ani ma'alin osah l'sha'arei mizrach. So we bring her to the eastern
gate, which is probably שער ניקנור, Sha'ar Nicanor, the Nicanor gate, which
is the main entrance between the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim into the
main עזרה Azarah of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So really that's
the halfway point
on in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. דאימר אמרת טהורה אני De'imar
amart tehorah ani, מעלין אותה לשערי מזרח. ma'alin osah l'sha'arei mizrach. מעלין
אותה, Ma'alin osah, what does it mean they bring her up? Charlie
has a picture.
I happen to be learning the מסכת מידות. Masechet Middos. There you
go.
He's learning מידות, Middos, so you have the map here. You have
the map of בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the שער ניקנור Sha'ar
Nicanor was the big gate and it had two smaller doors on
either side and had 15 steps going up to it. It's really
the central point especially for people who are ישראלים Yisraelim or don't
have any reason to be going into the עזרה. Azarah. That's where
people who are in בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would be hanging out.
It's called עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim because women were there but men
were there as well. Lots of different people who didn't have any
reason to go into the עזרה. Azarah. Okay. מעלין אותה. Ma'alin osah.
What does it mean they bring her up there? התם קיימא, Hasam
kayma, she's already there. Okay, because we said already earlier in the
process she had already been brought to שער ניקנור. Sha'ar Nicanor. So
what does it mean they have to bring her up?
Meaning that she was brought up to
the בית דין הגדול שבירושלים. Beis Din Hagadol shebiYerushalayim. The בית דין
הגדול Beis Din Hagadol is the לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagazis is on
the boundary between... Charlie can show you on the map, but the
בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, the לשכת הגזית, Lishkas Hagazis, they
sit, their לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagazis straddles the border between the עזרה
Azarah and עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. It has to be in
the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim part, which is lower, right?
When you go up the steps? But the שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nicanor
is also right at the edge. So there's no difference. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ומקיפין אותה ומקיפין אותה כדי ליגעה. U'makkifin osah u'makkifin
osah kedei l'yage'ah.
They make her walk all around the הר הבית Har Habayis to
tire her out so that she should be more weary and be
more willing to admit if she were guilty that she would be
more willing to admit, and therefore on the flip side to make
sure that the fact she's drinking the סוטה Sotah water is because
she really does believe that she's innocent. And this is comparable to
דתניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר בית דין מסיעין את העדים ממקום
למקום כדי שתטרף דעתן עליהם ויחזרו בהן. Detanya Rebbe Shimon ben Elazar
omer Beis Din masin es ha'edim mimakom lemakom kedei shetitaref da'atan aleihem
v'yachzeru bahen. That for witnesses to a capital crime, we also make
them schlepp all around in order to tire them out so that
we should try to confirm the fact that they're not telling false
testimony because again, in a capital crime, if the witnesses are lying,
then they're killing an innocent person. On the flip side we have
a מצוה mitzvah to actually tell their testimony if they're telling the
truth. So in order to try to create a disincentive to people
to lie, we really make it such a pain, but at the
same time they have to encourage them to say if you really
are telling the truth then you really have to do it and
it's a big מצוה. mitzvah. So this is a difficult thing of
really trying to ascertain the truth, that they add in this other
piece of trying to schlepp them around to tire them out. There
you go.
לשכת הגזית Lishkas Hagazis
is that tiny little square on the bottom side.
Okay. Surprisingly small. Surprisingly small, had to fit at least 71 people
in there. Okay. ששם משקים את הסוטה. Sheshem mashkim es haSotah.
So at the place, meaning at the שער המזרח, Sha'ar Hamizrach, that's
where they make the סוטה Sotah drink. בשלמא סוטה דכתיב והעמיד הכהן
את האשה לפני אדני Bishlama Sotah dechtiv vehe'emid hakohen es ha'ishah lifnei
Adonai because the פסוק pasuk says you have to do it לפני
ה'. lifnei Hashem. So if the woman has to drink לפני ה',
lifnei Hashem, so that's where it should be. מצורע נמי דכתיב Metzora
nami dechtiv and the מצורע, metzora, the משנה Mishnah had listed that
this is the place for סוטה Sotah and מצורע metzora and יולדת.
yoledes. So מצורע, metzora, מצורע נמי דכתיב והעמיד הכהן המטהר. metzora nami
dechtiv vehe'emid hakohen hamitaher.
The כהן kohen has to stand up the מצורע metzora again at
the entrance of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or at the entrance
of the משכן Mishkan and therefore that's the place where you go.
It's interesting of course that the מצורע metzora is excluded from living
even anywhere within the city of ירושלים Yerushalayim or any walled city
and then for the טהרה taharah process is brought back inside the
city and the symbolism behind that is very powerful. Okay. אלא יולדת,
Ella yoledes, but what about a woman who's given birth? מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, so why does she have to stand there? אילימא משום
דאיתא מקיימא
אקרבנייהו, Ilema mishum de'asa mikaima akorbaneihu, isn't it if you'll say it's
just because of the reason that anyone who's bringing a קרבן korban
has to be there to participate in the קרבן, korban, to watch
the קרבן, korban, and that's the reason why even for the קרבן
תמיד, Korban Tamid, the Jewish people, ישראלים Yisraelim had to come to
ירושלים Yerushalayim to be part of the מעמד Ma'amad as well, the
מעמדות, Ma'amados, that was in מסכת תענית. Masechet Taanis. דתניא אין קרבנו
של אדם קרב אלא אם כן עומד על גביו, Detanya ein korbano
shel adam karev ella im kein omed al gabav, a person can't
bring a sacrifice unless they're actually there or if they send a
שליח shaliach to bring it for... אי הכי זבין וזבות נמי *ihachi
zavin v'zavot nami*, so then shouldn't you say fine, so the rule
for יולדת *yoledet* should be also זב *zav* and זבה *zavah*? There's
no reason why the משנה mishna *mishna* should have listed יולדת *yoledet*
but not anyone else who's bringing a קרבן *korban* and the comparable
people who bring a קרבן *korban* of מחוסרי כפרה *mechusarei kaparah* are
זב *zav* and זבה *zavah*. הכי נמי ותנא חדא מניהו נקט *hachi
nami v'tana chada mineihu nakat*. No, they just, the משנה mishna. *mishna*
listed one, just יולדת *yoledet*, but really it meant all of them.
Fine. תנו רבנן tnu rabanan: *tanu rabanan*. תוספות Tosafot *tosafot* in a
number of places throughout ש"ס *shas* has a whole problem with the
fact that the משניות *mishnayot* in particular and תנאים *tannaim* use a
לשון *lashon* that sounds incredibly inclusive or exclusive, a very strong לשון
*lashon*, but then really there are all sorts of exceptions. How do
you deal with the fact that tannaic statements have lots of exceptions?
So תוספות Tosafot *tosafot* deals with that a lot of places.
תנא ושייר *tana v'shayer*.
Yeah, they have a תנא ושייר *tana v'shayer*, all kinds of things.
Okay. תנו רבנן *tanu rabanan*. אין משקים שתי סוטות sotos כאחת *ein
mashkim shtei sotot k'achat*. You cannot make two סוטות *sotot* drink at
the same time. צבי *Tzvi*?
A busy day. Okay, so this is an interesting question. Number one,
the point here
is the point of the fact that I forget who says this,
but someone brings from this a proof that you don't have to
wait until the רגלים *regalim*. סוטה Sotah *sotah* you do immediately because
if you would wait until the רגלים *regalim*, then you would probably
have a number of women who are סוטות *sotot* all at once
and you'd try to smush them all together. So the ברייתא braisa,
*braita* says אין משקים שתי סוטות כאחת כדי שלא יהיה לבה גס
בחברתה *ein mashkim shtei sotot k'achat kedei shelo yehei libah gas bachaverta*,
that she shouldn't be more haughty because she sees her fellow סוטה
Sotah *sotah* woman next to her because what would happen if one
of them is being very stubborn and the other one is being
very stubborn, then they'll both end up even if they were guilty
they would end up drinking the water. Yes.
Well, there's another practical matter. During the חגים *chagim* there's a zillion
things going on
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *beit hamikdash*. That's also true. That's
another good argument why not to push it off. But once they
came together,
is what this
is all about.
Yeah, that's also a good point.
That's the same reasoning that we don't bundle the slaves
together, right, having the slaves and servants there as well, right, is
that she shouldn't have לבה גס בחברתה *libah gas bachaverta*. Okay. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר לא מן השם הוא זה אלא אמר קרא
אותה לבדה *Rabbi Yehuda omer lo min hashem hu zeh ela amar
kra otah levadah*. It's not based on a סברא *sevara*. It's not
based on this idea of לבה גס בחברתה *libah gas bachaverta*. No,
it's a פסוק *pasuk*. It's גזירת הכתוב *gezeirat hakatuv*. אותה לבדה *otah
levadah*. The פסוק *pasuk* says just her by herself. It's an interesting
מחלוקת machlokes *machloket*. They both agree on the הלכה *halacha* but they're
disagreeing about the proof. One is saying that it's a סברא *sevara*
and one is saying that it's גזירת הכתוב *gezeirat hakatuv*. This is
one of the good examples of the fact that חז"ל *chazal* treat
a good סברא *sevara* as a דאורייתא *de'oraita*. Okay. ותנא קמא היינו
רבי שמעון *v'tana kama hinu Rabbi Shimon*. So the תנא קמא *tana
kama* is רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* דדרש טעמא דקרא *dedarish ta'ama d'kra*.
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says oh, I'm just telling you the reason
for the פסוק *pasuk*. He agrees that the פסוק *pasuk* says אותה
לבדה *otah levadah* but he's telling you the reason and therefore the
limitations on the דאורייתא *de'oraita*. The גזירת הכתוב *gezeirat hakatuv* is based
on the logic behind it which is שלא יהיה לבה גס בחברתה
*shelo yehei libah gas bachaverta*. This is a מחלוקת machlokes *machloket* between
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* in
other places in ש"ס *shas* about דרשינן טעמא דקרא *darshinan ta'ama d'kra*.
Can we apply an understanding of the reasons behind דרשות *drashot* and
the reasons behind פסוקים psukim, *psukim* to provide more parameters to the
הלכות *halachot* that we learn out from them? מאי טעמא קאמר *mai
ta'ama ka'amar*. So מה טעם אותה לבדה כדי שלא יהא לבה גס
בחברתה *mah ta'am otah levadah kedei shelo yehei libah gas bachaverta*. So
the reason why she should be by herself is so that she
should not have this haughtiness. מאי בינייהו *mai beinaihu*? So what's the
נפקא מינה *nafka mina*? איכא בינייהו רותתת *ika beinaihu rotetet*. A woman
who is particularly fearful and nervous about the סוטה Sotah *sotah* water.
So then even if she were accompanied by another סוטה Sota *sotah*
she wouldn't, we wouldn't have the fear that she would be emboldened
by having another סוטה Sota *sotah* with her. Interestingly enough, the תוספות
Tosfos, הרא"ש *Tosafot HaRosh* says רותתות *rotetot* plural because what if one
of them is, one of them is very fearful but the other
one is still cool with it? Then she'll be emboldened by the
other one even, so we should חושש *choshesh* to cover both bases.
Okay.
ורותתת מי משקין *v'rotetet mi mashkin*?
So can you really make someone who's totally fearful drink the water?
והא אין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות ain osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos *v'ha
ein osin mitzvot chavilot chavilot*. Meaning fine, you'll tell me just because
she's afraid, so then we don't have a fear about לבה גס
בחברתה *libah gas bachaverta*, so we could do two סוטות *sotot* at
one time? What do you mean? Who says we could do two
סוטות *sotot* at once? We have a better proof, אין עושין מצוות
חבילות חבילות ain osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos? *ein osin mitzvot chavilot chavilot*.
We can't bundle up our מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot* all together. Here רש"י
*Rashi* says, if you look in רש"י *Rashi*, the reason why we
don't do מצוות mitzvot חבילות חבילות chavilos chavilos. *mitzvot chavilot chavilot*. חבילות
חבילות *chavilot chavilot* רש"י *Rashi* says because שנראה כמו שהיה עליו למשאוי
*shenireh k'mo shehayah alav l'masoy*. It's like a heavy burden. וממהר לפרק
משאו *u'memaher l'farek masao*. It's like you're trying to get rid of
a heavy burden, people say come on let's you know let's daven
mincha we have to get it over with or something like that.
The sense of מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot* are just something to be יוצא
*yotzei* and move on and not something to really cherish and take
value in. So doing מצוות חבילות חבילות *mitzvot chavilot chavilot*, doing all
your מצוות *mitzvot* all at once is to try to rush through
it.
Okay, so תוספות Tosfos *tosafot* in מועד קטן *moed katan* actually has
different rationale for מצוות חבילות חבילות *mitzvot chavilot chavilot* and says much
more not that you're avoiding a negative value but you're actually embracing
a positive value. תוספות Tosfos *tosafot* there compares אין עושין מצוות חבילות
חבילות *ein osin mitzvot chavilot chavilot* to אין מערבין שמחה simcha בשמחה
*ein me'arvin simcha b'simcha*. That just like we don't have... the wedding
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed because we want to treat חול המועד
with the שמחה simcha it deserves and treat the wedding with the
שמחה that it deserves, so too each מצווה mitzvah should be kept
separate so that each one gets its own שמחה של מצווה simcha
shel mitzvah and each one gets its own focus. And one of
the אחרונים, Achronim, רבי יוסף אנגל, Rav Yosef Engel, notes actually an
interesting point based on a principle עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה, osek
b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah, so maybe the reason you can't do two
מצוות at once is because as soon as you're doing one מצווה,
mitzvah, it פוטר paturs you from the other מצווה, mitzvah, and so
then you can't be doing both at once just as a technicality.
Technically you don't have to, I mean...
Okay, well some אחרונים Achronim try to say that really you become
אסור assur to do the other מצווה mitzvah anyway, fine.
And here's the same מצווה mitzvah exactly. The other examples we see
with אין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות are things often like can you
use the same cup to say קידוש Kiddush and בנצ'ינג, Benching, or
קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה, Havdalah, and all different things like that?
So those are different מצוות that you're trying to push together as
opposed to the same מצווה mitzvah over and over again. But now
we have a ברייתא, braisa, okay. דתנן: desnan: אין משקין שתי סוטות
כאחת. ain mashkin shtei sotos k'achas. You can't make two סוטה Sota
women drink the water together. ואין מטהרין שתי מצורעים כאחת. v'ain metaherin
shtei metzoraim k'achas. And you can't do the purification ritual for a
מצורע, metzora, which involves the oil and the blood and the birds
and everything, you can't do them both together. ואין רוצעין שתי עבדים
כאחת. v'ain rotzin shtei avadim k'achas. And you cannot pierce the ear
of an עבד כנעני... eved K'naani... sorry, of עבד עברי eved Ivri
both at once. עבד עברי eved Ivri after... you could do one
after the other. You could do one after the other, but you
can't do them both together. עבד עברי eved Ivri after he served
for six years is given an opportunity to go free. And if
the עבד עברי eved Ivri says אהבתי את אדוני, ahavti es adoni,
I love the fact that I'm a slave, I love my master,
I perhaps love the fact that my master has given me a
wife... so then he gets his ear pierced and the Torah says
ועבדו לעולם. va'avado l'olam. Interestingly enough, there's a מחלוקת machlokes based on
this. What do you mean אין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות? Who said
piercing the ear of a slave is a מצווה? mitzvah? So it's
a מחלוקת machlokes between the חזון איש Chazon Ish and the מגן
אברהם Magen Avraham how to understand this. The חזון איש Chazon Ish
thinks it's really a רשות, reshus, it's totally optional. Even if the
slave comes to the master and says I want to stay your
slave, the master could refuse. And the מגן אברהם Magen Avraham says
once the slave actually wants to be נרצע, nirtza, then the master
has to do it, it becomes an obligation. Okay. ואין עורפין שתי
עגלות כאחת. v'ain orfin shtei eglos k'achas.
You can't do two עגלה ערופה egla arufa together. Obviously it would
be incredibly tragic for one city to have two kinds of עגלה
ערופה egla arufa type of homicide cases at once, but that would
be a case where you wouldn't be allowed to do them each
one... both together, you have to do them each one separately, לפי
שאין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות. l'fi she'ain osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos. Interesting
also to note that all of the examples in this ברייתא, like
Jenna said, are cases of doing two of the same מצווה mitzvah
together rather than doing different מצוות as a group.
Because no one's gonna say oh I can't דאוון daven and shake
a לולב. lulav. Right, so all these...
it's not that you can't do them at the same time, it's
that there's a whole preparation thing. With the עגלה ערופה, egla arufa,
you have to go out to the middle of nowhere...
Right, these are all kind of very ceremonial processes.
And as we said with the עבד... eved...
Oh, the עבד eved is also והגישו אל האלוהים, v'heigisho el ha'elohim,
you have to bring him to the court, you have
to... Right, you
don't just go out with
a מרצע... marzeia...
right, you just take him out and...
Anyway, you'll get into
that when you
get into קידושין, Kiddushin, it comes up in the first פרק perek
of
קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay. ואין רוצעין שתי עבדים כאחת ואין עורפין שתי עגלות
כאחת לפי שאין עושין מצוות חבילות חבילות. v'ain rotzin shtei avadim k'achas
v'ain orfin shtei eglos k'achas l'fi she'ain osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos. אמר
אביי ואיתימא רב כהנא: Amar Abaye v'isayma Rav Kahana: לא קשיא כאן
בכהן
אחד כאן בשני
כהנים.
lo kashya kan b'kohen echad
kan b'shnei kohanim. So the
answer is one כהן kohen can't do both, but
you
could do two סוטות really on the same day with two different
כהנים, kohanim, or even perhaps at
the same time with two different
כהנים kohanim because then the
כהנים kohanim are not
doing it
חבילות חבילות. The גמרא Gemara continues: וכהן אוחז בבגדיה. v'kohen ochez b'v'gadeha.
The כהן kohen holds onto her clothing.
So תנו רבנן: ופרע את ראש האישה... ufara es rosh ha'isha... first
he rips it and then he ties the חבל. chevel. Why don't
you just tie the חבל... chevel... No, but other questions, but I
mean ערווה, Ervah, right?
This is a question, the question is going to be here, how
much does it inspire הרהורין. hirhurin. So למימרא דרבי יהודה חייש להרהור.
lemimra d'Rabbi Yehuda chaish l'hirhur. רבי יהודה is concerned that people will
have sexual thoughts because of the סוטה sotah. ritual, ורבנן לא חיישי,
v'Rabbanan lo chaishi, רבנן don't care as much. והא איפכא שמעינן להו
דתניא האיש מכסין אותו פרק אחד מלפניו v'ha ipcha shamanin lehu d'tanya
ha'ish m'chasin oso perek echad milfanav because we know about when we
execute someone by סקילה, skilah, a man is totally naked except he
gets some kind of a loincloth, פרק אחד מלפניו, perek echad milfanav,
one piece of cloth in front. והאשה שני פרקים אחד מלפניה ואחד
מלאחריה, v'ha'ishah shenai perakim echad milfaneha v'echad milachareha, a woman gets like
a double loincloth, one in the front and one in the back,
מפני שכולה ערווה mipnei shekulah ervah doesn't mean that a woman's entire
body is ערווה ervah here, if you look in רש״י, Rashi, שבית
הבושת נראה משני צדדין, shebeit haboshet nireh mishenei tzedadin, a woman's genitalia
or perhaps in a sense is visible from both sides rather than
with a man, so a woman needs to be covered from both
sides but still the woman's entire torso would be uncovered when they
execute her by סקילה, skilah, and therefore it seems like even according
to that opinion we're less worried about
הרהורין. hirhurin. דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's רבי יהודה's position.
וחכמים אומרים האיש נסקל ערום v'Chachamim omrim ha'ish niskal arom a man
is stoned totally naked, ואין האשה נסקלת ערומה v'ein ha'ishah niskales aromah
no, a woman cannot be stoned naked at all, she has to
be clothed at the time of
stoning.
Right. It seems as though from this point forward he's using to
be operating under the assumption that she's guilty. So he's looking at
examples of like when we're executing. Right. Almost as if we're assuming
that we're executing someone for sure.
And also the thing to note as well is just the fact
that so many of the parallel examples are from מיתת בית דין.
mitat beis din. The witnesses, we tire out the witnesses just like
witnesses or we tire her out like we tire out the witnesses
for for a capital crime. Here the parallel is to סוטה sotah
and שריפה and the first תוספות on the next page which we'll
touch on hopefully in a second also. So we see here the
מחלוקת machlokes whether whether a woman would be stoned naked or not.
אמר רבא הכא טעמא מאי שמא תצא מבית דין זכאי ויגרו בה
פרחי כהונה.
amar Rava hacha ta'ama mai shema taitzi mibeit din zakai v'yigaru
bah pirchei kehuna. What if she leaves a בית דין beis din
meaning she leaves the סוטה sotah ritual totally innocent because she drank
the water and she didn't explode or she didn't die or whatever
it is, ויגרו בה פרחי כהונה v'yigaru bah pirchei kehuna and the
כהנים Kohanim who are hanging around in the בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash.
if you look in רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says מצויין בעזרה. metzuyin
ba'azarah. They're hanging out in the עזרה. azarah. An interesting question based
on the מחלוקת of whether or not the clothing בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna for a כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, whether the אבנט avneit is
made of שעטנז shatnez or not, is whether כהנים Kohanim are allowed
to just kind of hang around when they're not doing the עבודה.
avodah. Regular כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, if he's not doing the עבודה
avodah and if you think that the אבנט avneit is made of
שעטנז, shatnez, then he's not allowed to be wearing the בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehuna unless he's actually doing it. And then lots of different
answers in אחרונים achronim about how how to get around all those
interesting questions in that סוגיא. sugya התם הא מסתלקא. hasam ha mistalka.
So in that case it's because she she was killed so there's
no concern of הרהורין hirhurin in a case of a woman who's
executed so there's no concern about executing her naked but here
with a—I'm sorry, what do you mean? Aren't you worried about הרהור
hirhur at the time that she's naked?
No, we're worried about, see the concern here, ויגרו בה פרחי כהונה,
v'yigaru bah pirchei kehuna, that after she leaves the בית דין beis
din and she's innocent then all of these כהנים Kohanim are going
to see her whatever she's walking around with the clothing etc. that
they'll have some kind of a lust for her, they'll have some
kind of inappropriate thoughts about her, but in a case of a
woman who's being executed in בית דין beis din there's less of
a concern, we're not really concerned for things that that could be—yeah,
but only if she's pretty we're worried about her.
Again, and how much do you interpret that to mean that how
pretty does she have to be or how not? I don't know.
That's a good question. Still, ערווה's Ervah an ערווה, Ervah, you don't
say like okay well she's pretty she can leave her she's gotta
cover her but she's ugly she I mean like I don't
understand. For sure.
To me exactly that's the מחלוקת דלמימרא דרבי יהודה חייש להרהור ורבנן
לא חיישי. d'lemimra d'Rabbi Yehuda chaish l'hirhur v'Rabbanan lo chaishi. We're going
to see why in a second because הא אמר ha amar okay
וכי תימא אתי לאתגרויי בה אחרינתא. v'chi teima asi l'itgaru bah acharinsa.
So then shouldn't they just, you know, they would go after anyway?
אמר רבא גמירי דאין יצר הרע שולט אלא במה שעיניו רואות. amar
Rava gemiri d'ein yetzer hara sholeit ela bamah she'einav ro'os. No, a
person doesn't have any יצר הרע, yetzer hara, a person doesn't have
inappropriate thoughts or inappropriate perhaps sexual thoughts in this context particularly except
for something that a person has actually seen. Becomes an interesting question
regarding all other sorts of applications to
all other sorts of applications, Rabbi Linzer's podcast etc.
What's the I don't—no, meaning
exactly the point that in a case where where the woman were
executed and and then she's dead, then they don't see her again,
there's no concern. But in case of a married woman who's now
walking around town or whatever, that that these כהנים Kohanim will see
her and they'll their thoughts will
be—yeah, I don't understand that. Yeah. There's
another
רש״י. Rashi.
Oh so רש״י Rashi says because the concern even if they see
her and she disappears and she goes back to her husband or
whatever, that even then they'll be inspired to have inappropriate sexual thoughts
about
other
women. Yeah, okay. This is a good
question. Fine, and so the answer רבא *Rava*’s answer then is that
no, they'll only have יצר הרע *yetzer hara* about her and not
other women because they'll only have יצר הרע *yetzer hara* for the
woman who they actually saw but not another.
Meaning they won't see other women, but they'll see other women
they won't see other women naked, right.
What because the person's יצר הרע *yetzer hara* is only aroused for
a person that they actually see but not whatever. Ask Rabbi Linzer.
אמר רבא *Amar Rava*. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה
קשיא *deRabbi Yehuda ad deRabbi Yehuda kashya*.
So it sounds like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s opinion contradicts his other
opinion because here in the סוטה *Sotah* he seems to be more
concerned for הרהורים *hirhurim* but in the case of סקילה *skila* he's
less concerned about הרהורים *hirhurim*. דרבנן אדרבנן לא קשיא *DeRabbanan ad deRabbanan
lo kashya*. But this is a question. Right, this is a question.
Are you going to say, are you going to say that רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is still a problem but the רבנן *Rabbis* to
each other are not a problem? אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava:
דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא כדשני דרבנן אדרבנן נמי לא קשיא
*Ella amar Rava deRabbi Yehuda ad deRabbi Yehuda lo kashya kedshani deRabbanan
ad deRabbanan nami lo kashya*. So it's not a problem either way.
הכא טעמא מאי *Hacha ta'ama mai*? So what's the reason? משום ונוסרו
כל הנשים *Mishum venisru kol hanashim* because all of the women have
to be
punished for... it's a פסוק *pasuk* from יחזקאל *Yechezkel*. In other words,
in some way the other women are going to have to see
the shame that comes about to the סוטה *Sotah* woman and therefore
they'll learn from her example. התם אין לך ייסור גדול מזה *Hatam
ein lecha yisur gadol mizeh*. But there's no... and in the case
of execution
there's no need for any other humiliation because the capital punishment is
itself a punishment enough. Okay. וכי תימא לעבי בה תרתי *Vechitei tema
la'avi bei tartei*? So shouldn't we do both, meaning shouldn't we expose
her in public as well as execute her? אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה אמר קרא ואהבת לרעך כמוך ברור לו מיתה יפה
*Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha amar kra veahavta lere'acha kamocha
beror lo mita yafa*. This is the דרשה *drasha* that gets brought
up a million times in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*. Whenever we do capital punishment
it has to be ברור לו מיתה יפה *beror lo mita yafa*,
it has to be an appropriate death and the רבנן *Rabbis* apply
this דרשה *drasha* to each of the four מיתות בית דין *mitot
beit din* to try to take what it sounds like from the
תורה *Torah* explicitly for the most part
and back it off in a way that preserves the physical integrity
of the human body.
I think it's Professor Lorberbaum in Israel recently wrote a book about
this about basically the core principle of rabbinic understanding of capital punishment
is this idea of צלם אלוקים *tzelem Elokim*, that if the human
being has a physical form that is in some way representative of
God, then capital punishment needs to be carried out in such a
way that does not deform the human body. And therefore ברור לו
מיתה יפה *beror lo mita yafa* doesn't necessarily mean the most pleasant
death but is the most... the death that leaves the human body
most יפה *yafa*. It leaves the body intact, leaves the body totally
unspoiled.
Look at תוספות *Tosfot*, the top תוספות *Tosfot*, תוספות *Tosfot* says... sorry
we're not up to that yet, never mind. Okay. ואהבת לרעך כמוך
ברור לו מיתה יפה
*Veahavta lere'acha kamocha beror lo mita yafa*, yes. Is the shame in
public? It's almost a... a fine that she's killed.
Yeah,
that's for sure.
That's exactly the concern.
And then does she deserve that even...?
That's a great question and for sure that's part of what's problematic
about the סוטה *Sotah* process.
One possibility is again even a woman who is innocent of having
had an adulterous affair has still disobeyed her husband's explicit request to
her that she not be in ייחוד *yichud* with this particular man
and she went into ייחוד *yichud* anyway in a public way with
עדים *edim* who really were able to testify to it so in
a certain sense she still is throwing off some of the responsibilities
of her relationship with her husband and she does disrespect that in
a certain sense. But again she's innocent of adultery, she still did
something fishy.
It's
only related to the paramour in a certain sense.
Yeah, well right. He only dies if she ends up being guilty
but otherwise he's totally innocent which is another interesting question.
It's a punishment for both of them.
For sure. וכי תימא לעבי בה תרתי *Vechitei tema la'avi bei tartei*.
Okay. ואהבת לרעך כמוך ברור לו מיתה יפה *Veahavta lere'acha kamocha beror
lo mita yafa*. לימא דרב נחמן תנאי היא *Lema deRav Nachman tannai
hi*. דלא פליגי דעלמא אית להו דרב נחמן *Delo peli de'alma it
lehu deRav Nachman*. So רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*’s opinion, so we're going
to say so what does רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* say? והא בהא
קמיפלגי *Veha bahai kamilya palgi*. מר סבר בזיונא עדיף לה טפי מצערא
דגופא *Mar savar bizyona adif lah tfei mitza'ara degufa*. One says that
being... her being embarrassed, being naked in public is better than the
pain, צערא דגופא *tza'ara degufa* of her physical pain because when a
woman would be stoned or a person is stoned the רבנן *Rabbis*
understand that the clothing provides some cushioning from the stones so if
you wear clothing when you're executed then the physical pain is worse
because it takes longer to die but then you're less emotionally embarrassed
of being naked in public. But if you die naked then you'll
die faster because the stones will not be cushioned but you'll so
you'll have less pain but more embarrassment. So one opinion מר סבר
בזיונא עדיף לה טפי מצערא דגופא *mar savar bizyona adif lah tfei
mitza'ara degufa* ומר סבר צערא דגופא עדיף לה טפי מבזיונא *umar savar
tza'ara degufa adif lei tfei mibizyonei*. One says it's better to be
physically embarrassed rather than and to have more pain. Meaning they both
apply the principle of מיתה יפה, you have to provide the best
death possible, but they disagree about how to do that. הייתא מכוסה
לבנים hayta mechusa levanim so what if she's wearing white clothing? והתניא
ve-hatanya תניא tanya אם היו שחורים נאין לה im hayu shechorim na'in
la if she looks really good in black clothes מכסין אותה בבגדים
מכוערים mechassin ota bi-vgadim mecho'arim so you dress her up in ugly
clothes or dirty
clothes.
Does it mean that they'll come to embarrass her?
No, they'll come to have sexual thoughts about her, they'll come to...
not worried about at all like, "Oh yeah, you know, I saw
you in the בית המקדש." Beit Ha-Mikdash Not worried about that?
It doesn't seem that that's the concern, at least from the גמרא
Gemara for sure. And again, part of the discussion in later מפרשים
mefarshim is the whole סוטה ritual, like we said, even a woman
who's in the case ספק safek guilty or maybe she's totally innocent,
etc. So how are we allowed to embarrass her? Embarrassing a woman
and actually on דף י' daf yud תוספות are going to ask,
embarrassing a person in public we say is like שופך דמים. shofech
damim. So doesn't that mean that it's יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve-al
ya'avor to not embarrass somebody? And תוספות has an answer there, but
that really is the question of, like, the severity of this ritual
is that you're embarrassing someone without necessarily any good reason.
I don't understand though who's deciding who's נאה na'a and who's not?
The water decides.
No, נאה. na'a. Meaning רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says if she's נאה
na'a you don't do it.
Oh, נאה. na'a. The גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to answer it. In
a certain sense, it may be that this סוגיא is treating it
as if we're kind of ignoring that clause in the משנה mishna,
to a certain extent.
Does she have to do it all the time? Is that really...
I'm not really sure. I don't have a good answer for that.
It's a very good question of, like, it says specifically for a
woman who's נאה, na'a, like what does it mean נאה? na'a? Good
question. Okay, הייתא מכוסה... hayta mechusa... so we said הייתא מכוסה בלבנים.
hayta mechusa bi-levanim. היו עליה כלי זהב hayu aleha klei zahav what
if she's wearing jewelry, gold jewelry? פשיטא. pshita. So we have to
take it off? פשיטא? pshita? השתא ניבולי מנבלה hashta nivulei menabla because
we're trying to make her look disgusting, we're trying to make her
look embarrassed. הני מיבעי ליה דתימא בהני אית
ליה בזיונא טפי
hani miba'ei lei detema behani
it lei bizyona tfei maybe if she's wearing her jewelry it's even
more embarrassing, כדאמרי אינשי kid'amri inshi שלח ערטיל ורמי מסאני. shlach artil
u-remi masanei. You might say like the common proverb, a person who
walks around naked but with shoes on, and that's more embarrassing than
being totally totally naked because, like, what are you even doing? It
seems illogical, it seems out of place. So a woman who's going
through the סוטה ritual and then is also wearing her fancy jewelry
might make it even more embarrassing for her compared to her former
state.
Like oh, you once had all this jewelry and now...
Exactly. So you would say קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, we
don't necessarily apply that principle. אחר כך מביא חבל, achar kach mevi
chevel, so then he brings the rope, the Egyptian rope. The ירושלמי
Yerushalmi says the reason why it's an Egyptian rope is because she
did כמעשה ארץ מצרים ke-ma'aseh eretz Mitzrayim or perhaps she maybe did
מעשה מצרים ma'aseh Mitzrayim so you bring in the Egyptian rope. Another
interpretation is probably not חבל מצרי chevel mitzri but חבל מצאוי. chevel
matzui. It's just a common... the common rope was woven from the
palm fronds and it's a rough material and it's a very coarse
kind of a rope and that's another possibility for how to understand
that. So בעי מיניה רב אבא מרב הונא: bei minei Rav Abba
me-Rav Huna: חבל המצרי מהו שיעכב
בסוטה? chevel ha-mitzri mahu she-ye'akev be-Sota? Okay, so is the reason for
this חבל המצרי, chevel ha-mitzri, is this מעכב? me'akev? Is it a
necessary part of the סוטה ritual? משום שלא ישמטו בגדיה מעליה mishum
she-lo yishmetu vigadeha me-aleha so that her clothes don't fall down, הוא
משום שלא ישמטו... hu mishum she-lo yishmetu...
wait, keeping her clothes...
I mean, we were just going through how it's important to humiliate
her.
So you don't want to do too much, or because of the
concern of her being naked in the בית המקדש or something like
that.
But she should...
it should be that her clothing should be torn open, but then
also so it doesn't totally fall down. She's not going to be
standing there totally naked, it's that מגלים את לבה, megalim et liba,
you tear open the shirt of her...
before you rip it, if
you rip it and then it...
you don't have to actually מגלים את לבה.
megalim et liba.
You rip it and
then it... then it... Yeah, for sure.
I don't have such a good handle on what exactly is going
on here.
Right, it's a temporary thing and then they still let her kind
of wrap herself.
Because אינו דומה ניקור, eino dome nikur, right? That
was
the
משנה. mishna, It's a bit unclear.
So they're trying to ask, is the חבל המצרי chevel ha-mitzri מעכב
me'akev or not? Because the question is going to be: Okay, so
if the reason is משום שלא ישמטו בגדיה מעליה, mishum she-lo yishmetu
vigadeha me-aleha, if the reason is that her clothes don't fall down,
בצלצול קטן נמי סגי, bi-tziltzul katan nami sagi, so then you should
be able to use even a very small cord, a small belt.
Okay, או דילמא משום דאמר מר היא חגרה לו בצלצול לפיכך כהן
מביא חבל המצרי וקושר לה למעלה מדדיה.
o dilma mishum de-amar mar hi chagra lo bi-tziltzul le-fichach Kohen mevi
chevel ha-mitzri
ve-kosher la le-ma'ala mi-dadeha. So if the reason is because she used
this fancy belt to entice her her lover, then the כהן Kohen
has to bring a different kind of a material, a חבל המצרי
chevel ha-mitzri in order to hold up her clothes.
I think you read וקושר לה למעלה מדדיה ve-kosher la le-ma'ala mi-dadeha
is a משנה, Mishnah right?
The next part? Okay, ואל חבל המצרי, ve-al chevel ha-mitzri, go. וקושר
לה למעלה מדדיה, ve-kosher la le-ma'ala mi-dadeha, they tie it above her
breasts, מעכב. me'akev. So it sounds like then that it should be
מעכב. me'akev. אמר ליה תניתוה. amar lei tanituha. Okay, ואחר כך מביא
חבל המצרי וקושר לה למעלה מדדיה כדי שלא ישמטו בגדיה מעליה. ve-achar
kach mevi chevel ha-mitzri ve-kosher la le-ma'ala mi-dadeha kedei she-lo yishmetu vigadeha
me-aleha. No, because we have a different version of the משנה, Mishnah,
a longer version, a more expanded version that says no, the reason
you bring it is just so that her clothes don't fall down.
Fine. Okay, so it's not מעכב. me'akev.
Using the imagery when you tear, it's like breaking up all the
imagery
related to the relationship in a sense. Right, get some dynamic into
those clothes, but the tearing is...
Right, it has to be like a symbolic tearing in some sense,
right. תוספות, the top תוספות asks about basically where does this rope
come from? Do you buy this rope? So it says from the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi that they buy the rope from משיירי הלשכה, Mishearei Halishka,
they buy it from public funds. And תוספות then has a question:
ולאידנא איסורא שנחנק בו וסייף שנהרג בו, Velidana issura shenechnak bo vesayif
shene'erag bo, do you buy the sword that you use for beheadings,
do you buy the handkerchief you use to hold people's necks for
חנק, chenek, do you also buy those with public funds? In other
words, the question is how much can we draw a parallel again
between capital punishment and סוטה. Dan, do you have a question?
So we keep going. וכל הרוצה לראות בה יראה, Vechol harotzeh liros
ba yireh, anyone who wanted to see is allowed to see. הגופא
קשיא, Hagufa kashia, it contradicted itself. אמר כל הרוצה לראות בה יראה,
Amar kol harotzeh liros ba yireh, it sounds like anybody who wants
to see can come see. אלמא לא שנא גברי ולא שנא נשי,
Almah lo shena gavrei velo shena nashei, it sounds like there's no
difference between men and women. והדר תני כל הנשים מותרות לראותה, Vehadar
tanei kol hanashim mutarov lirosa, women are allowed to see her; נשים
אין אנשים לא, nashim in anashim lo, it sounds like yes for
women and no for men.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, תרגמא אנשים. Targama anashim. Now just say that
it means men, meaning the first part is just men.
נשים, Nashim, אנשים. anashim.
תרגמא אנשים. Targama anashim. Oh, you're saying, fine. תרגמא אנשים, Targama anashim,
that even the first part is just saying for the women to
come and not men. אמר ליה רבא: Amar lei Rava: והא כל
הרוצה לראות בה יראה, Veha kol harotzeh liros ba yireh, but still
it says whoever wants to come can come.
ויראה קתני. Veyireh katani. אלא אמר רבא: כל הרוצה לראות בה יראה
לא שנא גברי ולא שנא נשי, Kol harotzeh liros ba yireh lo
shena gavrei velo shena nashei,
נשים חייבות לראותה. nashim chayavot lirosa. Whoever wants to come, men and
women have a choice whether they want to
come or not.
They have to amend the משנה Mishnah. because it contradicts. ונשים חייבות
לראותה, Venashem chayavot lirosa, the women who are present have to go
see, שנאמר ונוסרו כל הנשים ולא תעשינה כזמתכנה,
shene'emar venivsaru kol
hanashim velo taasena kezimaschena, that the women have to go see so
that they don't end up doing the same kind of זמה, zimah,
the same kind of inappropriate sexual activities that the סוטה may or
may not have been guilty of.
Plus we know that the men have
to go see
and the
women
have a
choice, exactly, unless the כהנים. Kohanim.
Right. We could read the next משנה, Mishnah the next גמרא Gemara
is going to go on to a long אגדתא, so we'll start
with that tomorrow when Rabbi Linzner gets back. We can just read
the משנה. Mishnah So the משנה says: במידה שאדם מודד בה מודדין
לו. Bemidah she'adam moded bah modedin lo. The idea of מידה כנגד
מידה, middah keneged middah, the way a person measures out his or
her own life, that's how God is then going to measure it
back against such a person.
היא קישטה עצמה לעבירה, Hi kishta atzmah la'aveirah, she dressed herself up
with jewelry for her sin, המקום ניולה, hamakom nivalah, God then takes
away. Assumption of guilt for sure, that is part of the way
the משניותא Mishnayota are very problematic. המקום ניולה. Hamakom nivalah. היא גלתה
את עצמה לעבירה, Hi giltah es atzmah la'aveirah, and she revealed herself
for a sin, המקום גילה עליה, hamakom gilah aleiha,
so then God reveals her. בירך התחילה בעבירה, Beyerach hitchilah ba'aveirah, she
started her sin with her thigh, which really means the genitalia, תחילה
ואחר כך הבטן, techilah ve'achar kach habeten, and afterwards her womb because
presumably the concern of pregnancy from the adulterous relationship. לפיכך פלקה הירך
תחילה ואחר כך הבטן, Lefichach palkah hayerech techilah ve'achar kach habeten, so
therefore her punishment goes in that order as well. ושאר כל הגוף
לא פלט, Veshear kol haguf lo palat, but the rest of the
body is not damaged by the סוטה water because it only affects
those parts of the body.
But didn't we actually
think that the difference between the
פסוקים, psukim yeah it's going to get into that. The פסוקים talk
about it in one way and the גמרא is going to take
it from there and this is going to go into a long
גמרא about all different
things. I didn't really prepare from here on so I don't want
to keep going.
So with that we'll end here, start with the משנה tomorrow on
כ' עמוד ב'. chaf amud beis.